[Music]
atrial fibrillation or afib is the most
common clinical arrhythmia meaning
abnormal heart rhythm affecting millions
of americans recognized as a global
public health problem due to its
significant burden of death and disease
resulting from stroke heart attacks and
heart failure
is there any particular diet that may
help prevent or treat it well recently
we learned what not to eat low carb
diets are associated with increased risk
of developing atrial fibrillation for a
variety of reasons first of all people
on low carb diets may be eating fewer
anti-inflammatory foods like vegetables
fruits and whole grains reducing intake
of these anti-inflammatory foods may be
one of the important mechanisms for the
risk of getting a fib
secondly a low carbohydrate diet means
increased protein and fat consumption
which may stimulate oxidative stress the
formation of free radicals which was
also demonstrated to be associated with
afib
finally the effect could result from the
increased risk of other cardiovascular
disease which can set you up for afib
and indeed low carb diets are associated
with an increased risk of overall
mortality dying from any cause as well
as specifically dying from
cardiovascular disease and dying from
cancer
dietary recommendations for patients
with heart rhythm disorders is
essentially the opposite
of a low-carb diet centered on a
day-to-day basis around fruits
vegetables grains beans and nuts with
seafood at most a few days a week eggs
dairy and chicken on more like a once a
week basis and other meat on more like a
once a month basis in part because we're
trying to cut down on saturated and
trans fats
whole food plant-based diets emphasizing
whole grains legumes beans split peas
chickpeas and lentils
vegetables fruits and nuts and excluding
most or all animal products may play a
special role as they not only maximize
protective foods but also exclude
potentially harmful animal foods for
example there's persuasive evidence that
avoidance of certain foods may
beneficially affect atrial fibrillation
such as the avoidance of dark fish and
alcohol
the dark fish thing comes from the
framingham heart study by dark fish they
mean salmon
swordfish bluefish mackerel and sardines
and they found an exploratory analysis
that those participants who consumed
more than four servings of dark fish
like salmon or sardines a week were at a
whopping six-fold higher risk of
developing a-fib though the intake of
fish in general didn't seem to have any
effect
we're not exactly sure why alcohol is so
bad when it comes to arrhythmias but we
might have as much as an eight percent
increase in the relative risk of afib
associated with each drink one might
have per day though drinking coffee or
caffeine in general does not seem to be
related to arrhythmia risk
where plant-based diets really shine
though is an afib risk factor management
plant-based diets may reduce the
likelihood of many traditional risk
factors that are associated with afib
including hypertension
hyperthyroidism obesity and diabetes
high blood pressure is one of the major
risk factors accounting for about
one-fifth of all new cases of afib which
is where plant-based diets can come in
improving vasodilation the ability of
your arteries to expand naturally in
addition to the anti-inflammatory
antioxidant effects and increase
potassium intake and decrease blood
viscosity or sludginess
in terms of hyperthyroidism excluding
all animal foods from one's diet is
associated with half the prevalence of
hyperthyroidism compared with those who
eat meat with vegetarians and fish only
diets associated with intermediate
protection
having excess body fat may be
responsible for about another fist of
all afib cases but the good news is
significant weight loss is associated
with a six-fold greater freedom from
atrial fibrillation
you can see that of those with afib who
started out overweight but lost 10
percent or more of their body weight
five years later only 10 percent ended
up with afib whereas those who lost less
than three percent or gained weight 60
percent ended up with afib six times
more
here are all the atrial fibrillation
risk factors that can be prevented
arrested or even reversed
with a healthy enough plant-based diet
high blood pressure type 2 diabetes
obesity systemic inflammation and heart
disease in light of these findings
dietary modifications are of paramount
importance
but you don't know if it could actually
cure atrial fibrillation until you
put it to the test
unfortunately all we have are case
reports but this one is quite compelling
an 82 year old man presents with
polypharmacy
meaning on a bunch of different
medications due to coronary artery
disease heart attack history ischemic
cardiomyopathy high cholesterol high
blood pressure and persistent atrial
fibrillation who presented with memory
loss
cognitive impairment fatigue and
weakness
now if you're not going to change the
diet and lifestyle that led to all the
problems in the first place then drugs
can certainly be better than nothing yet
commonly used blood pressure and
cholesterol lowering medications provide
actually little absolute risk reduction
and pose significant risk of adverse
effects as i've explored before
so this guy decided to start treating
the underlying cause so he started a
whole food plant-based diet with
moderate physical activity resulting in
a rapid reduction of high cholesterol
and high blood pressure and the
discontinuation of statin
anti-hypertensive and beta-blocker drug
therapy
the patient also reported reversal of
impaired cognition and symptoms
associated with atrial fibrillation and
ischemic cardiomyopathy including
lightheadedness fatigue and weakness
check out these numbers started out on
all his medications uh started eating
healthier in february and his ldl bad
cholesterol dropped 37
down to 72
and you say yeah but he's still on
cholesterol lowering statin drugs but
even after his doctor discontinued it
and his blood pressure meds his
cholesterol stayed down and his blood
pressure completely normalized
okay but what happened to his atrial
fibrillation completely
resolved
here's how the patient described it
in december 2017 i suffered a near fatal
heart attack and was rushed to the
hospital i immediately had a stent put
in the following day i was prescribed a
number of drugs to manage my condition
my brain fog got worse and i felt tired
all the time
i decided
enough was enough i had already lost
four years of my life to
medication-induced brain fog i wasn't
gonna sacrifice more
i've been eating a wholesome
mediterranean diet but i was then
educated on the benefits of cutting out
all the crap and now i have the strength
to lift weights and walk and run on the
treadmill an hour every day i feel more
alive than i have for years i wake up
each morning with a clear head and happy
heart grateful to not have to take a
handful of drugs
even though i'm not perfect with my diet
i've seen huge benefits from eating this
way my blood tests have shown remarkable
improvement which keeps me motivated to
stay on track
because of my improvement my
cardiologist suggested i could let go of
his last remaining drug
eating this food gave me an opportunity
to reclaim my health
[Music]
you